Guide to the Maurice Sand Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Maurice Sand Papers
1833-1995
1848-1889
GEN MSS 1463
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.75
(10 boxes)
The Maurice Sand papers contains family and professional correspondence, publishing contracts, writings, drawings, posters, and other material by or about the nineteenth-century author, illustrator, and puppeteer. The collection offers substantial documentation of Sand's theatrical work from the late 1840s to the 1880s; included are holograph scripts, scenarios, or posters for over forty puppet plays created by Sand. The collection also includes three novel drafts, a set of playing cards issued by an unidentified French publisher with humorous additions in ink and pencil by Sand, as well as a manuscript libretto, manuscript music fragments, with vocal lines only, and related correspondence for Callirhoé (circa 1886), an opera by Auguste Bazille (1828-1891) with text by Armand Silvestre (1837-1901) based on a scenario by Sand.
Sand, Maurice, 1823-1889
Bazille, Auguste, 1828-1891 ( Callirhoé)
Silvestre, Armand, 1837-1901 ( Callirhoé)
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 10: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Les Amazones on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, Frederick W. Hilles Fund, and Mary Flagler Cary Fund, 2011-2017.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence and Contracts, 1848-1929. II. Puppet Theater, 1848-1995. III. Writings, 1841-1886. IV. Artwork, 1833-1887. V. Other Papers, 1853-1960.
Biographical / Historical
Maurice Sand (1823-1889), son of author George Sand (1804-1876) and Casimir Dudevant (1795-1871), was a French writer, artist, and puppeteer. Sand studied painting with Eugène Delacroix in the early 1840s, and later wrote and illustrated several novels and monographs on topics ranging from theater history to the natural sciences. Sand directed an amateur puppet theater at the Sand family estate of Nohant from 1847 to 1876, and at his Paris residences, for which he authored plays, designed sets, and sculpted and operated wood puppets.
Sand married Lina Calamatta in 1862, with whom he had a son, Marc-Antoine (1863-1864), and two daughters, Aurore (1866–1961) and Gabrielle (1868–1909). Sand served as mayor of the Nohant-Vicq commune in 1848, and from 1875 to 1879.
Related Materials
Associated material of the same provenance: the Solange Clésinger-Sand Papers (GEN MSS 755) and the Edmond Plauchut Papers (GEN MSS 1462), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Scope and Contents
The Maurice Sand papers contains family and professional correspondence, publishing contracts, writings, drawings, posters, and other material by or about the nineteenth-century author, illustrator, and puppeteer. The collection offers substantial documentation of Sand's theatrical work from the late 1840s to the 1880s; included are holograph scripts, scenarios, or posters for over forty puppet plays created by Sand. The collection also includes three novel drafts, a set of playing cards issued by an unidentified French publisher with humorous additions in ink and pencil by Sand, as well as a manuscript libretto, manuscript music fragments, with vocal lines only, and related correspondence for Callirhoé (circa 1886), an opera by Auguste Bazille (1828-1891) with text by Armand Silvestre (1837-1901) based on a scenario by Sand.
Authors and publishers -- France; Authors, French -- 19th century -- Archives; French literature -- 19th century; Operas -- Librettos; Operas; Puppet plays, French -- 19th century; Drawings; Playing cards; Posters; Authors -- France -- 19th century; Bazille, Auguste, 1828-1891; Calamatta Sand, Lina, 1842-1901; Sand, George, 1804-1876; Sand, Maurice, 1823-1889; Silvestre, Armand, 1837-1901; Théâtre de Nohant (Nohant-Vicq, France); Théâtre des marionnettes (Paris, France)
- Correspondence and Contracts, 1848-1929; 1860-1889; Series I; 0.25; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Personal Correspondence, and Publishing Contracts and Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence and Contracts, comprises both personal letters and professional communications with publishers. Correspondence with Auguste Bazille and Armand Silvestre regarding the opera Callirhoé is located in Series III. Writings. Twentieth-century third-party correspondence by Aurore Sand regarding family property is located in Series V. Other Papers.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1848-1929
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
    Personal correspondence contains autograph and copied letters exchanged between Maurice Sand and family members, acquaintances, and politicians. Letters concern the health of family members, awards and mayorial duties bestowed on Sand, and comments on Sand's writings.
    - Cavour, Camillo (from), 1860-12-22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Clésinger-Sand, Solange (to), copy, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Copy in the hand of Lina Sand of an 1885 letter from Maurice to his sister.
    - Delasalle, Louis Albert (from), 1879-07-20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - D'Emery, [M] (to and from), 1878, and undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Flaubert, Gustave (from), copy, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Copy in the hand of Lina Sand of an undated letter (circa 1868) from Flaubert commenting on Sand's novel Miss Mary.
    - Gaubert, Docteur (from), copy of 1837 letter, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Matheson, A. for the Société de l'Agriculture de Châteauroux (from), 1870-06-18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Petit, [?] (from), 1848 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Renan, Ernest (to), 1876; 1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Accompanied by a letter from Noémi Renan to Aurore Sand (1929).
    - Sand, George (to), 1864; undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Letter sent on behalf of the puppet characters of the Théâtre de Nohant, and two letters regarding Maurice's son's illness.
    - Sand, George (to and from), copies, circa 1840 - 1854 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Copies in the hand of Aurore Sand of letters exchanged between George and Maurice Sand, and of a letter in Italian by Frederic Chopin to George Sand.
    - Unidentified correspondents (to), 1875-1888 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Publishing Contracts and Correspondence, 1860-1901
    Arranged alphabetically by publication title.
    Publishing contracts and correspondence document Maurice Sand's business relations with publishers for a significant number of his literary works, as well as the involvement of George and Lina Sand in negotiating terms of publication. Key figures of nineteenth-century French publishing are represented, including Michel and Kalmus Lévy (firms Michel Lévy frères until 1875 and Calmann-Lévy thereafter), and Albert Lacroix (firm A.Lacroix, Verboeckhoven).
    - L'Augusta, 1872-1901 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Contract with Michel Lévy frères (1872), bills from Typographie Chamerot et Renouard (1900-1901), and correspondence between Lina Sand and Georges Rochegrosse (1896-1899) regarding the edition illustrated by Rochegrosse.
    - "Callirhoé - Quatrième partie", 1863-08-10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Letter from Maurice Sand to Emile [Aucante] regarding a mistake in the printing of "Callirhoé" in Revue des Deux Mondes, July 1863 issue.
    - Le coq aux cheveux d'or, 1866-1867 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Correspondence between Albert Lacroix and Maurice Sand, and between Lacroix and George Sand. George Sand's response is a copy in the hand of Lina Sand.
    - La fille du singe, 1885-08 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Contract with Paul Ollendorff.
    - "Funestre oubli", 1889-01-12 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Rejection notice from Frédéric Masson, editor of Paris illustré
    - Mademoiselle Azote, 1869-05-17 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Contract with Michel Lévy frères.
    - Mademoiselle de Cérignan, 1874-04-01 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Masques et bouffons, 1860-1869 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Contract between Maurice Sand and Ernest Bouju (1860), letter from A. Laplace regarding a lawsuit for counterfeited products based on Sand's illustrations (1869).
    - Miss Mary, 1868-03-24 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Letter from Michel Lévy negotiating publishing terms for Miss Mary in relation to the sales of Callirhoé.
    - Le monde des papillons, 1862-1866 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Contract with Ernest Bouju for Deux jours dans le monde des papillons (1860), contract with J. Rothschild for Le monde des papillons (1866).
    - Raoul de la Chastre, 1865-03-03 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Letter from Michael Lévy frères confirming acceptance of contract.
    - Six mille lieues à toute vapeur, 1862-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Letter from Michel Lévy frères confirming acceptance of contract.
    - Le théâtre des marionnettes, 1889-01-07 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Contract with Calmann-Lévy.
    - Unknown work, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Letter from Paul Ferrier to Lina or George Sand regarding the eventual publication of a work by Maurice Sand.
- Puppet Theater, 1848-1995; 1848-1886; Series II; 3.33; (3 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Scripts and Scenarios, Posters, and Related Material.
  Series II, Puppet Theater, includes scripts, scenarios, manuscript posters, drawings, and print material documenting the work of Maurice Sand in directing an amateur puppet theater at the Sand family estate of Nohant and at his Paris residences. All writings and posters are holograph unless specified otherwise in the file description.
  - Scripts and Scenarios, 1848-1886
    Arranged chronologically.
    - "La Bastille", 1848 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Cleanthe", 1848 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Dupathy à Modène", 1848 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Ida", 1848 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "Les malheurs de la guerre", 1848 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 131)
    - "Noces et festins", 1848 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - "Une nuit à Ferrare", 1848 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "Le pape", 1848 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "Le spectre", 1848 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - "La vengeance", 1848 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "La vie de campagne", 1848 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "Janvier 1789", 1849 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 132)
    - "Avril 1789", 1849 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 133)
    - "La méprise", 1849 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - "Combrillo de sombrero", 1854-10-23 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 134)
    - "Robert le maudit", 1855-10-15 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 135)
    - "Léonora", 1858-02-28 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - "Noël", 1869 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 136)
      Accompanied by "Le tombeau des secrets", a Christmas gift list for family members and friends.
    - "La goule de Tornemar", copy by Armand Silvestre, 1869-01-31 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - "Toutyfaut", 1873 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "J'ai oublié mon panier", 1875-04-09 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "La chambre bleue: Comédie de famille, mêlée de chiens et de bruits en un acte", copy by Lina Sand with holograph additions, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "Balandard aux enfers", character lists and tirade script, 1886-04-19 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "La fille du colonel", undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "Une soirée à Paris", copy by Lina Sand with holograph additions, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Untitled play, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Fragments of scripts and scenarios, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Empty envelopes, undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 137)
      Empty envelopes for chronological groupings of theater scenarios and scripts with labels in contemporary hand. Envelopes had been separated from the material prior to their arrival at the Beinecke Library, and some of the years indicated on the envelopes are not represented among the scripts and scenarios of this collection.
  - Posters, 1850-1873
    - "L'enlèvement", 1850-08-29 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 138)
    - "Le quine, ou noir et blanc", 1850-09-29 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 138)
    - "Pierrot Savetier", 1852-06 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 138)
    - "L'appartement à louer", 1853-08-07 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 138)
    - "Robert le maudit", 1855-10-15 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 139)
    - "Pourpre et sang", 1855-11-25 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 139)
    - "La catalpa", 1856-09-10 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 140)
    - "Jacques", 1857-09-22 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 141)
    - "L'émigré", 1857-10-08 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 141)
    - "Daniel", 1857-10-30 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 141)
    - "Le Dalès", 1857-11-19 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 141)
    - "Eustache", 1858-09-23 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 142)
    - "La morte vivante", 1859-11-20 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 142)
    - "Le sauvage ou le retour d'Amérique", 1862-04-25 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 143)
    - "Noces et festins", 1867-02-27 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 144)
    - "Une tempête dans un coeur de bronze", 1867-11 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 144)
    - "Un prince", 1867-12-01 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 144)
    - "La goule de Tornemar", 1871-05-10 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 145)
    - "Divertissement pour Mme Aurore et Gabrielle", posters and programs, 1872-01-01 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 145)
    - "Nouveaux débuts", 1872-02-18 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 145)
    - "Une page d'histoire", 1873-09-21 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 146)
    - "Toutyfaut", 1875-10-10 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 147)
  - Related Material, 1883 - 1995, and undated
    Organized alphabetically by document type.
    - Blank invitation card for a puppet show, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Clipping "La soirée théâtrale: Les marionnettes de Maurice Sand", from Le Figaro, 1883-05-22 (Box 3, Folder 49)
      - Restricted fragile: original clipping, 1883 (Box 10, Folder 150)
        Conditions Governing Access
        Box 10: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    - Exhibit brochure Decor, marionnettes et théâtre de George et Maurice Sand, 1939; 1995 (Box 3, Folder 50)
      Accompanied by the clipping "Les marionnettes chez George Sand" from Le Petit Parisien (1939) (preservation photocopy).
      - Restricted fragile: original accompanying clipping, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 151)
    - Festschrift "George Sand and the Puppet Theater at Nohant" by Julia Bloch Frey, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Notes "Théâtre de Nohant et les marionnettes", in the hand of Aurore Sand, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Photographic print of two puppets, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Print "Théâtre des marionnettes - représentation dans l'atelier de M. Maurice Sand", from Le Monde Illustré (1858), undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 148)
    - Studies of costumes [for the play "Claudie"], pencil, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Theater decor, watercolor and ink, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Writings, 1841-1886; Series III; 1.75; 5 boxes + 1 oversize folder
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series III. Writings, contains manuscripts of narrative and non-fiction writings by Maurice Sand, including holograph drafts with corrections for three novels ( Le coq aux cheveux d'or, La fille du singe, and Palabran ), a script for the opera Callirhoé (accompanied by a partial music score and related correspondence with composer Auguste Bazille and lyricist Armand Silvestre), and notes on various topics of interest to Sand.
  - "Article de George Sand sur Raoul de la Chastre", manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
    Copy in the hand of Aurore Sand, and photocopy of the text in another hand.
    - Restricted Fragile: thermofax photocopy, undated (Box 10, Folder 152)
  - "Assolements" and "cotyledons", notes, holograph, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Callirhoé: Opéra en 3 actes et 5 tableaux, 4
    - Script with drawings of costumes and decors, holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - "Récit de Callirhoé", manuscript music fragments, undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 149)
    - Related correspondence, 1886 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Notes, holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Catalogue raisonné des lépidoptères du Berry & de l'Auvergne, preparatory maps and tracings, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - "Les chiens: 2 jeux de 52 cartes", notes, holograph, undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Le coq aux cheveux d'or, novel, holograph, 1867; 11 (Box 4, Folder 63-73)
  - "Le diable des lagunes", short tale, holograph, undated (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - La fille du singe, novel, holograph, 1886; 8 (Box 5, Folder 75-82)
  - "Gastéropodes", classification, holograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - [Humorous poems], undated (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - "Mélanges manuscripts inédits" notebook, holograph, circa 1841 - 1881 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    Notebook containing holograph texts and notes on a variety of topics, some of which relate to published works such as Le coq aux cheveux d'or, Miss Mary, and Callirhoé.
  - "Notes sur l'artillerie fournies par A. Bazille", holograph, circa 1861 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Notice sur un atelier de silex taillés des temps préhistoriques aux environs de La Châtre (Indre), holograph, 1879 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - [On butterflies and fishes], notes, holograph, undated (Box 6, Folder 88)
    Includes tracings for a work on lepidoptera.
  - [On Cantal and Berry], notes, holograph, undated (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - [On clothing history], notes, holograph, undated (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - [On French grammar], notes, holograph, undated (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Palabran, novel, holograph draft and notes, undated; 5 (Box 7, Folder 92-96)
  - Le Pied-sanglant, play script, manuscript with holograph annotations, undated (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - "Quelques mots sur la lune...(tirés des notes d'un voyageur)", holograph, undated (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - "Transfusion - Littré", notes, holograh, undated (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Unknown work, holograph page, undated (Box 7, Folder 100)
- Artwork, 1833-1887; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series IV. Artwork, contains small drawings, sketches, and watercolors on various themes, as well as French playing cards featuring humorous variations drawn by Maurice Sand. A sketchbook dating from Sand's childhood highlights his early interest for drawing. The series does not contain artwork identified as relating to Sand's illustrated publications. Additional artwork pertaining to puppetry is located in Series II. Puppet Theater.
  - Caricatures of M. and Mme Prudhomme, ink, undated (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - "Chateau de Presle", pencil tracing, undated (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - Fossils and bones, ink and pencil, undated (Box 8, Folder 103)
    Captions in the hands of Maurice and Aurore Sand.
  - French playing cards, ink and pencil drawings on printed suits, undated (Box 8, Folder 104)
    Thirty playing cards featuring humorous figures drawn by Maurice Sand around the standard French suits, particularly the hearts and the tiles.
  - Ghost and soldier, ink and watercolor, undated (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - Jewelry sketches, pencil, undated (Box 8, Folder 106)
  - Map of the Nohant region, ink, undated (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - "M. Maurice Sand aux échecs" drawing, 1887-09-28 (Box 8, Folder 108)
  - Miscellaneous small sketches, pencil and ink, undated (Box 8, Folder 109)
  - Portrait of Aurore Sand, pencil, 188[5?]-05-07 (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - "Prentigarde - Peyre Levade - Avise Toi", ink, undated (Box 8, Folder 111)
  - Pseudo-scientific and historic drawings, ink and pencil, undated; 3 (Box 8, Folder 112-114)
    Humorous captions in the hands of Maurice and Aurore Sand.
  - Sketchbook with childhood drawings and notes, ink, circa 1833 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    Sketchbook from Maurice Sand's childhood featuring ink drawings of soldiers, an illustrated "Almanach de France, 1833", multiplication tables and other learning exercises.
  - "Souvenir d'un voyage autour de la table", pencil, 1861 (Box 8, Folder 116)
  - Study of a flower, pencil and watercolor, 1861-07-20 (Box 8, Folder 117)
  - Studies of figures, ink and pencil, undated (Box 8, Folder 118)
  - Studies of plants, pencil, 1845 (Box 8, Folder 119)
- Other Papers, 1853-1960; Series V; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by document type.
  Series V. Other Papers, comprises all other items in the collection relating to Maurice Sand, including photographic portraits, print material about Sand, files on family property, and honorary titles.
  - Booklet Maurice Sand by George Ay, undated (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Clipping from L'écho agricole, 1872 (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - Clippings of obituaries for Maurice Sand, 1889; 1939- (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - File on Le Christ en croix by Peter Paul Rubens, undated (Box 8, Folder 123)
    Material documenting the provenance of the painting in the Sand family: contemporary inventory of personal property brought by Maurice Sand to his marriage, later statement of ownership by Aurore Sand, and photograph of painting.
  - File on portrait of Marie Delaporte by Maurice Sand, 1951-1960 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    Correspondence between Aurore Sand and third parties, a photographic print of the painting, and a copy in the hand of Daniel Delaporte of the 1860 contract between Maurice Sand and actress Marie Delaporte.
  - Photographic portraits of Maurice Sand, 1878; undated; 2 (Box 8, Folder 125-126)
  - Prints of drawings and paintings of Maurice Sand, undated (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - Short manuscript note, undated (Box 8, Folder 128)
  - Titles and awards, 1853-1874 (Box 8, Folder 129)
  - Visiting cards, undated (Box 8, Folder 130)